consider the function f of x equals x
squared where the output is obtained by
multiplying the input by itself the
graph of this function looks like this
if we plot a point on the curve we can
draw a line called the tangent line
which looks like the curve locally then
we can compute the slope of this line at
that point and now let's compute the
slopes of the tangent lines at every
point along the curve like this we see
that as we move along the curve the
slope of the associated tangent line
changes we can go one step further and
create a new set of axes on this set of
axes we're going to plot the y
coordinate as the slope for the
corresponding x coordinates in the curve
above when we do that we see a linear
function map out in particular the slope
function for f of x equals x squared is
the line y equals 2x we use the notation
F Prime of x equals 2x for this slope
function and say the derivative of x
squared is 2x because the derivative
function is the function that outputs
the slopes of the tangent lines to
verify this fact requires more work but
at least we can see that the formula
holds visually